少爷！准备好了
Young master, we are ready
辛苦了！少爷
What's a hard job for you, young master
少爷！擦个汗吧
The towel, young master
师爷，少爷写的是甚么？
What did he write?
名字
His name!
好棒！原来少爷会写自己的名字
Great! Young master knows how to write his name!
对呀
Yes!
好字
Nice calligraphy
走开
Get lost
好字！龙飞凤舞，苏察哈尔灿
Nice calligraphy! So Cha Ha Yee Chan!
你念反了，老爷
It's reversed, Master
灿尔哈察苏
Chan Yee Ha Cha So
好小子，但是别骄傲，知道吗？
Good boy, but, don't be proud! Got me?
爹，我们苏察哈尔家
Dad, since the first emperor of the Ching Dynasty,
自太祖皇帝到现在
our family
都没有几个会写字的
has been illiterate
现在可不同，我的儿子你的孙儿阿灿
But not, my son, that's your grandson,
他会写自己的名字
he knows how to write his name!
爹，这可是非同少可
Dad, it's very great!
今天会写字
He knows writing now,
他朝必成大学士
he will be scholar one day
今天会写名
Now, he knows how to write his name,
他日一定会生子
he will have a son later
少爷，你真是要好好地学习写字
Young master, you should try hard to learn
阿灿，先把它裱起来
Chan, I think, we should mount it
裱起它
OK
师爷，把它挂在最当眼的地方
Professor, show it in some obvious places
这样吧，师爷
By the way, one minute,
你先揹著它簪花挂红，游行威风一下
why don't you carry it with traditional decoration in the street?
走吧
Let's go!
阿灿，来⋯坐⋯
Chan, come and sit…
你这么争气，我也很安慰
I am so pleased that you are that hard working and filial
你听我说，爹是有名的败家儿
Listen to me, I am notorious of being a spendthrift
家里的财产也败得差不多
My fortune is almost used up
说难听一点，日后我两脚一伸
If I die one day,
你个王八蛋，怎么到这里来讨饭？
you should depend on yourself
向来我都是靠自己
I used to depend on myself
十万两一张，省一点花啊
The cheques worth 100,000 taels! Don't be an extravagant spender
茂利，把我的西洋帽拿来
Give me the imported hat
你去哪，阿灿？
Where are you going? Chan!
今晚我做大寿
I am having a grand birthday party tonight
你贵庚？
How old are you?
廿五岁大寿，早点到
25 years old. Come earlier
做大寿你也得先把头发梳整齐
But you should dress up first
老是一个乞丐的模样
You are like beggar!
乞丐会那么有钱？我也想当
How can a beggar be that rich?! I do want to be a rich beggar!
那寿头真是⋯
That fat-headed…
过来，过来
Come over here
老爷，甚么事？
What's the matter?
那臭小子的寿帖真威风
The invitation card of my son is great!
他日老爷做大寿，要比他威风
If I hold a birthday party in future, I want a better invitation card!
皇爷，你觉得广东大戏怎样？
Your Majesty, how do you think about the Cantonese Opera?
地方戏曲，当然不及京戏
For sure, it can't compete with Peking Opera!
但也算是一种见识
But, I appreciate viewing this
打赏⋯打赏
Money…
恭喜苏翁生辰快乐
Happy birthday to you, Mr So
我家破人亡、贫病老弱
I am homeless and sick…
无亲无故、妻离子散
I am poor, I am damn poor!
打赏个救命钱　　怎么搅的，死乞丐！
- Please give me some money    - Kidding? Damn you beggar!
你个王八蛋，怎么到这裏来讨饭？
How can you beg here?
我打⋯
Go to hell!
打赏　　是，少爷
- Give him tips    - Yes, young master
这样也有打赏？
Are you kidding? How can you give him tips?
乞丐也是人
A beggar is a man too
只要有钱的都可以来
Everyone can come here if he has money
你这个月来这里
Your living,
吃饭看戏宵夜嫖妓，我包
including the expenditure for hooking, I will pay for you!
你包？
You pay it?
不可以吗？
So what?
可以，可以
Nothing!
大爷进我间房吧⋯　　请你跟我来
- Come into my room…    - Please follow me.
苏⋯翁
Mr So!
是⋯
Hello…
你好吗，鸨母？
How are you, Madam Pimp?
你真坏，有名字你不叫，叫我鸨母
It's very bad of you to call me that!
大家坦白一点不好吗？
Just be frank, why not?
要坦白吗
You should be frank!
你的帽子像披麻带孝似的
Your hat, is like the mourning uniform!
你老爸死了吗？
Has your dad passed away?
这样说大家才开心嘛
I feel happy to talk in this way
赵先生这趟帮本官扫平长毛贼
Mr Chiu, you helped me to terminate the Hairy Gang,
皇上一定重重有赏
the emperor will give you award for this
那就有劳皇爷在皇上面前
I'll appreciate it if you
多说几句好说话
speak something nice in front of the emperor
大戏做完了，请用毛巾
Please have the towel
苏翁来了⋯
Mr So has come
苏翁，恭喜发财
Congratulations!
这边⋯这边
This way…
苏翁，今天是你的好日子，很高兴吧
Mr So, today is your big day, you must be very happy!
我们有几位新来的姑娘，保证你满意
We have some new girls, you must be satisfied with them
金鱼还是木鱼？
What are they? Gold fish, or cooked fish?
少爷，甚么金鱼、木鱼？
What does that mean?
傻瓜，金鱼只可以看
You idiot! Gold fish is for watching only
木鱼则可以碰嘛
Cooked fish can be eaten
那当然要木鱼
Cooked fish of course
你们还不过来待候客人⋯
You, cooked fish, why don't you come and serve Mr So?
苏翁，今天是你的大日子
Mr So, you are the superior master today
你想要怎样的女人，你说就成
What kind of woman do you want? Just tell me
随便，女人都是一样的
I won't mind, every woman is just the same
没甚么特别
Nothing special
苏翁，甚么事？
Mr So, what's the matter?
我给人挑了一下
I am attacked
甚么？
What?
谁胆敢挑你？让我打她的咀
Who dared so? I will hit that bastard's mouth for you
不是用咀
She didn't use her mouth
是用眼睛
She used her eyes
诱惑中带有煞气，这种眼神我没见过
Tempting, and I smell blood I haven't seen such eyesight before
究竟是何方神圣？
Who is she?
这位如霜姑娘是客串
Miss Yushang comes to be a part-time hooker only
赵大人有没有兴趣和她摆房？
Is Mr Chiu interested to sleep with her?
你应该先问皇爷才对
You should ask His Majesty first
怎么样，皇爷？
How is it? Your Majesty?
大家自己人，何必客气呢？
We are friends, just go ahead if you want!
赵先生，请随便
Mr Chiu, help yourself
那我就却之不恭了
Thank you then
摆房
The room service please
如霜，快点下来见赵大人
Yushang, come and greet Mr Chiu
姐姐，就是他
Sister, he is the one we want
杀阿爹的人就是他
He killed dad
我知道，镇定点
I know, stay calm
走吧
Let's go
失陪　　赵大人
- May I be excused    - Mr Chiu
如霜姑娘到
Miss Yushang has arrived
小女子如霜，拜见赵大人
How are you, Mr Chiu?
果然是美人
A pretty woman!
赵大人，那今晚⋯
Mr Chiu, about tonight…
银票十万两
100,000 taels
如霜姑娘今晚要陪我家少爷
if Miss Yushang sleeps with our young master tonight…
没空招呼你
You are not welcome
各位⋯真不好意思
I am sorry, I am damn sorry
有甚么意见吗？
Don't you have any objection?
让我来⋯让我说句公道话
Let me say something fair
只要你们谁能付超过十万两银票
If any of you can offer more than 100,000 taels
如霜姑娘就陪谁
Yushang will sleep with whom
千万不要伤和气，对不对？
Don't quarrel because of such a small amount, isn't it right?
这位朋友真舍得花钱
Pal, you are a big spender
银票实在太普通
The cheque is too simple to me
我有一颗朝廷大内的定风珠，无价宝
I have a pearl which is granted by the Royal family, it's invaluable!
我还是比较喜欢珍珠
I love the pearl more
赵大人，我回房间等你
Mr Chiu, I will wait for you in my room
这颗珠值十万两吗？
Does the pearl worth 100,000 taels?
十万两你还嫌少吗，姑娘？
Don't you think that's too little for you?
我也喜欢银两，只是不喜欢你
I love money too. But, I don't like you
够坦白，我真的非常喜欢
You are frank! I love it very much
苏翁⋯
Mr So…
没相干
It doesn't matter,
一定是我今天的帽子和发型不配
I think, my hat doesn't match me
如霜姑娘看不上我，是我该死
Yushang doesn't like me, I deserve it
你明白就好了
I am glad you understand this
放心，我还有很多很漂亮的姑娘
Don't worry, I have many pretty girls here
鸨母，那今晚就倚仗你了
I trust your arrangement
这与我无关
None of my business
大胆！放肆
How bold are you?
螳螂拳？像模像样的
Mantis Fist? It seems to be powerful
奏乐
Music!
先放好
Keep this
鹤咀
See my Crane's Fists!
虎爪
The Tiger's Claws!
螳螂怎跟老虎斗？何况我还有一只鹤
How can a mantis fight with a tiger?
虎鹤双形我也会
I know Tiger Claws and Crane's Fists too!
那你试试看我的螳螂
Well, try my mantis!
好⋯好
Bravo…
我的螳螂拳再破你的虎鹤双形
Your Tiger's Claws are defeated
原来不是虎鹤双形
Actually it's not Tiger's Claws,
是孔雀开屏
it's beggar's fists!
难怪比较差
That's why it's too weak
动作蛮快
You move fast!
看来你比较像样
It seems to be powerful…
年青人，不知天高地厚
Kid, you don't know how the wind blows
广州将军到
The general of Canton has arrived
走开⋯
Get lost…
谁敢欺负我的儿子，我就射谁
Who dares bully my son, let me teach him a lesson
老爷
Master
不用害怕，阿灿，谁欺负你？
Don't panic, Chan who bullied you?
是我欺负别人
It's me who bullied others
甚么？你欺负别人？
What? You bullied others?
他有多少家财？他够不够资格
How much does he have? Is he qualified to be bullied by you?
老爷！是他们
Master, they are the ones
谁？
Who are they?
你看看就知道
Just take a look
铁帽子王？
The King of Iron Hat?
送贺礼
Send the gift
阿灿
Chan
人家送那么厚的礼就不要再欺负他
They send you such a valuable present, you'd stop bullying them
来⋯拿去打赏给这里的姑娘　　老爷
- Come on, give tips to the girl here    - Master
令牌上写著「铁帽子王僧格林参」
King of Iron Hat, Seng-ko-lin-ch'in is written on the medal
你胆敢抢皇爷的令牌？
How dare you seize the medal of His Majesty?
把他锁起来
Cuff him
等一等！根据大清律例
Hold it, according to the Ching's law,
身为朝廷命官，不得嫖妓
Courtier is not allowed hooking
你现在身在怡红院
Now, you are in the brothel
知法犯法，该当何罪？
Do you know you have violated the laws of Ching?
那么你呢？
How about you?
你说我？　　是
- You mean me?    - Yes!
对呀，我是来⋯
That's right, I come…
来拉⋯　　拉你
- to arrest…    - You!
他！　　拉他
- Him!    - Arrest him
我身为广州将军
I am the general of Canton,
当然要来拉你这害群之马
so I should arrest those bad people
还有⋯还有
By the way…
还有甚么？说吧
What else? Go ahead
今天是清太祖皇后叶赫拿拉氏的忌辰
Today is the birthday of the ex-Empress Dowager
身为京官罪加一等
So your crime is doubled
可以问斩
It may lead to capital punishment
斩他⋯斩他
Kill him…
根据大清律例
According to the Ching laws,
任何人不束辫子也要问斩
anyone without a tail should be killed
那你是要⋯
So you…
还想不想看？
Do you want to see my hair?
再多也有，傻瓜
You can see as much as you want! Fat-head
不用再说，斩他
Cut the crap, just kill him
好了好了，玩完了
OK, it's finished
苏将军，大家玩得那么开心就算了吧
General So, let's play happily together, so forget it
我今晚还没玩过
I haven't played!
皇爷
Your Majesty,
没想到在这里会让他们打扰你的雅兴
a rascal has ruined the atmosphere here,
小人安排不周
I should be blamed for poor arrangement
这与你无关
None of your business
我们走
Let's go
老爷！这个不能惹，见好就收
Master, you can't fool this guy. Let's go
收吧
OK, go
大事化小，小事化无
Just forget the trouble
少爷，你的帽子
Young master, your hat
真是高手
He is great!
莫大叔，酒菜已经加了断肠散
Uncle Mok, the dishes are all poisoned
好！赵无极暗算我们帮主
Chiu assassinated our Master
和太平天国的几名将领
and some generals of The Taiping Reign
还嫁祸给我们丐帮
And he framed us, the Beggars Association, to be the assassins
弄得江湖上的兄弟
Thus made us
人人也瞧不起我们
to be despised by the world
说我们投靠了朝廷
Saying that we became the dogs of the government
这个仇今天可以报了
I should ask him to pay for it
他们的先天罡气很厉害
His initial power is harmful
你们待会见他没上当，千万别出手
Don't take action until he is trapped
因为凑合我们几个也不是他的对手
Because we can't defeat him even if we group together
我会尽量诱他到床边
I will try my best to seduce him to the bed
长老，有人来
Senior, somebody is coming
大家准备⋯
Get ready…
如霜姑娘，我们又见面了
Miss Yushang, we meet again
怎么是你？赵大爷呢？
Why do you come here? Where is Mister Chiu?
赵大爷的定风珠
The pearl of Mr Chiu is broken
给苏翁一打就变成珍珠粉末
by Mr So and became pearl powder
我冲水喝了
I have drunk it
你不要看苏翁的头发像扫帚
Don't judge Mr So from his hair,
其实他为人很有情趣
he is really romantic and funny
但是⋯
But…
但是甚么，十万两我已拿了
Stop, I have taken his money, 100,000 taels you know?
我不会还给他的
I won't give it back
说到苏翁的为人⋯
About the personality of Mr So…
废话少说，鸨母
Cut the crap, pimp!
你先出去
Leave here first
是的⋯是的
Yes, you are right
七姑娘⋯　　将就一下⋯
- Miss Seven…    - Just accept this
这个是谁？
Who is this guy?
我不知道
I don't know
姑娘，首先有个好消息
Miss, first of all, I have good news for you
我很喜欢你
I love you
这对我来说是一个坏消息
To me, this is a bad news
我早知道你会这样说
I know you will reply like this
闲话休提
Cut the crap
我愿意出一百颗珍珠
I wish to pay you 100 pearls
希望如霜姑娘今晚能够陪我把酒谈欢
for your company tonight
我不想跟你多说
I don't want to talk to you
请你出去
Please get out
我果然没选错人
I haven't chosen the wrong one
好，我先饮为敬
OK, I will drink this wine first
不要喝⋯
No…
实在让我太感意外
It surprised me
姑娘
Miss
放手
Hands off!
原来你会武功
You know kung fu?
不，我根本就不会武功
No, I don't know Kung-fu at all
我求求你别再缠著我
I beg you, stop bothering me
我不会陪你
I won't accompany you
如霜，从来没有人这样对我
Yushang, no one treats me like this
我发觉我已经爱上了你
I have found that I am in love with you
你说甚么？
What?
我说，我已经爱上了你
I have been in love with you
你没有弄错吧？
Are you kidding?
绝对没有！我决定要娶你
I am not kidding, I decided to marry you
你有神经病
Are you nuts?
不是吧
Kidding?
原来有人藏在这里
Is there anyone hiding here?
正好，我正想找个证人
That's good, I want a witness
证人？　　对
- Witness?    - Yes
我就对著你的宝剑发誓
I swear in front of your sword
我是真心要娶如霜姑娘为妻
I do want to marry Miss Yushang as my wife, I am sincere
若然有半句假话，天打雷劈
If I cheat, I will be killed by thunder
姐姐，我真的替你兴奋⋯
Sister, I feel excited for you
唏！
Hey
你以为当我丈夫那么容易吗
Don't you know it isn't that easy to be my husband?
要怎样才可以当你丈夫呢？
How can I be your husband?
我要他武功盖世，状元之才
I want him to be the superior Kung-fu master
一人之下，万人之上
Be the top of all
那你是否做得到？
Can you do that?
让我想一想
Let me think for one second
做得到
I can do it
好
OK
待你做得到的时候，才回来找我
Do it first and then look for me
既然如此，我想我们要先定婚期
Well, I think we should fix a date for our wedding
因为做状元对我来说易如反掌
Because, this is too easy for me to be the Kung-fu scholar!
好！那也应该给我时间作考虑
OK, but you'd give me some time to consider it
没问题，我就在外面的花园等待答复
No problem, I will wait for your answer outside the garden
不见不散
I won't leave until seeing you
变态
Crazy!
丐帮办事，闲杂人等立即离开
We come for the Beggars Association, those unrelated persons leave at once
大人，半炷香的时间刚刚好
Sir, the timing is right
现在路上很安全，请上路
The road is safe now, please go
好！非常好
Good, very good
起轿！
Let's go!
糟糕！我们来晚了
Shit, we are late
都是那个人碍事！
That Manchurian should be blamed
姐姐⋯姐姐
Sister…
甚么事？
What's the matter?
那个神经病还在
The idiot is still there
不如杀了他
Let's kill him
算吧！他不是有心阻碍我们
Forget it, he doesn't mean to bother us
由他吧
Let him go
你不是喜欢他吧？
Are you fond of him?
你胡说甚么？
What did you say?
赵无极一日不死
I won't fall in love with anybody
我也不会想这些事
until Chiu is killed
何况是他
Especially him
赵无极武功很高
Chiu is good at Kung-fu
莫大叔说不会降龙十八掌便打不过他
Mok said, we can't defeat him unless using the “Dragon Killing Palms”
那我岂不是嫁不出吗？
So, I can never marry!
行吧！别发情
Let's go, if you want to marry
何方妖孽？竟敢来嚇我？
What evil are you? How dare you scare me?
苏翁，我是鸨母⋯
Mr So, it's me!
你是鸨母？
You are the pimp?!
是的
Yes!
胸部那么平，你的奶子呢？
You have a flat figure, where are your busts?
那么早，还未睡醒⋯
It's early in the morning, they haven't woken up yet
这次没有把你打死，算是你走运
It's lucky of you for not being killed
以后没有化粧不要四处走，知道吗？
Don't go around if you haven't made up yet
不会了，不会了
I won't do it again
你不用等如霜姑娘了，她已经走了⋯
Stop waiting for Miss Yushang, she left
走了？
What?
那究竟如霜姑娘去了哪里？
Where is she going?
听说，她⋯她去了京城
She… she is going to Peking
京城？
Peking?
男儿为国家⋯
Men should contribute to the country
⋯辫子怎样戴⋯
Where should I put my pigtail?
挥啊！挥啊！
Swing and swing…
我拉长它又弹它⋯
I pull it and play it…
阿爹
Dad!
我决定上京考文武状元
I decided to join the examination for the Scholar of Martial Arts
阿灿
Chan
爹等你说这句话，等了二十五年
I have been longing for this word for 25 years
为了苏察哈尔家，你应该这样做
For the sake of our family, you should do that
别误会，我这样做并不是为谁
Don't misunderstand it, I do it not for no one
只是为了一个女人
But for a woman
英雄
What a hero!
为妞死，为妞亡，为妞上京考状元
For a girl, you want to be the Scholar of Martial Arts!
何家女子？
Who is that girl?
怡红院金牌清官人如霜姑娘
The hooker of Yee Hung Brothel, Miss Yushang
妓女？
For a hooker?
有何不妥？
What's wrong with it?
品味与别不同，真是能人所不能
You have different taste, you are great!
阿爹钦佩你
I am admiring you!
我陪你上京
I will accompany you to Peking
二，三，四，五，六
2, 3, 4, 5, 6
来了，老爷
I am coming
少爷上京赴考，我们搬家
Young master is going for the examination, let's move to Peking too
你们不要追了
Stop chasing,
这些鸡不带了，京城多的是
we won't take the hens with us
你这个笨蛋小心点
Be careful!
弄花了我的东西，我不会放过你
If you break my stuff, I will teach you a good lesson
小心点
Be careful!
老爹，早
Good morning Dad
早
Good morning
真的全部都搬走？
You want to move everything to Peking?
当然
Sure
留件衣服给我穿啊
Please leave me a cloth
小孩子怕甚么呢？
You are only a kid, you don't need this
我不小了
But I am not small
呸！比我大吗？
Are you bigger than mine?
小看我？
You despise me!
总有一天比你大
Mine will be bigger than yours one day
有谁愿意脱下衣服来给我穿一下
Let's find something, say trousers to cover it
没眼看
I don't want to see it
你们站著干嘛？还不把它搬走
Why are you standing here for? Why don't you remove it?
屋那么大，何时才搬妥
It's a hard job to remove such a big house!
请大家卖力点，好不好
Please, work hard, men!
数三声！一，二，三，推
Ready, 1, 2, 3, push!
推⋯
Push!
小心推
Be careful!
绑牢一点⋯绑牢一点
Tie it well…
老爷，树也要搬？
Master, do you want to move the tree too?
当然
Sure,
否则我到京城那有荔枝吃？
or how can I eat Lychee in Peking?
推到那边⋯推到那边
Push it over…
小心点⋯小心我的荔枝
Be careful
小心我的荔枝，笨蛋
Take care of my lychee, you fathead!
赵无极这趟协助微臣
Chiu helped me to terminate
到广西剿平长毛余孽立功不少
the Hairy Gang in Kwangsi
微臣特意带他来见皇上
So I bring him here to greet Your Majesty
好！朕现在赐你为都察院副左都御史
Fine, I am now appointing you to be the Deputy Secretary
希望你日后好好为大清效力
Hope you will serve our Ching Dynasty wholeheartedly
谢主龙恩
Thank you, Your Majesty
皇上，赵先生一身奇技异术
Your Majesty, Mr Chiu is a magician
不如请他示范一下，让皇上开开眼界
Why don't you ask him to show you something?
异术？
Magic?
赵先生，你就示范给朕看
Mr Chiu, then show me your magic
是
Yes, Your Majesty
大惊小怪！退下
There is nothing surprising, go
是
Yes
微臣大胆，让皇上受惊
I am sorry for scaring you
如果这个女人是真的就好了
If this girl is real, that's fantastic!
站好！快点
Hurry up!
甚么事⋯甚么事？
What's the matter?
来⋯进去
Come on, go in
甚么事？
What's the matter?
躲进去
Hide in
准备好了，少爷
Get ready, young master
来
Come on
全部站好别再动
Freeze, don't move
那么香？你是飘红
Sweet smell, are you Piu Hung?
少爷你很棒，我喜欢
You are great! I love it
靠拢一点
Closer
那么大？一定是小小
So big! You must be Small!
少爷你很坏，这样说人家
You are bad, how can you say so to me?
你是大嘛
You are big!
怀孕的也有？骗不倒我
What? Pregnant woman? You can't cheat me
你是爹
You are a dad.
你很坏！这样也给你猜中
How bad are you, how can you guess that?
聪明，聪明
Good boy
阿爹还想作弄你一下，好棒好棒
I wanted to trick you actually, you are really smart
好了好了，少爷明早要考试
Young master has to join the examination tomorrow,
别玩得太疯
stop playing
出去，出去
Get out…
阿灿，你明天考试
Chan, have you prepared
准备好了没有？
for your examination?
准备甚么？我赢定了，你不知道吗
What should I prepare? I must win, don't you know that?
知道
Yes I do!
你这样的态度，我就有信心
I have faith in you from seeing your behaviour!
阿灿，这位是郑世伯
Chan, this is Uncle Cheng
明天郑世伯做主考
He will be the examiner
你来打个招呼
Say hello to Uncle Cheng
郑世伯，招呼不周
How are you, Uncle Cheng?
你看
See
我的儿子是否状元脸？
Doesn't he seem to be the winner?
要看他的造化了
It depends on fate.
老郑，你给我的考卷
Cheng, I've asked someone
我已经找人在做
to finish the papers which you gave me
不会改了吧？
Will the questions be changed?
考卷方面是没问题了
Don't worry about the question paper
至于临场考弓箭、骑马
But about the test of arrows shooting,
举石、搏击、兵器
riding, boxing and weapons…
就全靠他自己
He should try his best
这一点你放心
Don't worry
我的儿子十八般武艺样样精通
My son is keen on martial arts.
那二百万两可否酌量减一点？
So, can I deduct some from the payment of 2 million taels?
人情归人情，数目一定要分明
We are friends, but that is business
决定布个雁行阵，马队前驻中锋营
Let the horse teams be the pioneer
弓队侧翼，枪队殿后
The arrows teams go sideways, the gunmen stay back
武状元初赛，考生进场
The candidates come in
举不起来
I can't lift it
留力而矣
I don't want to waste my force
无耻？无耻你娘
Shameless? Damn you!
十分！
Oh, 10 marks
武状元决赛现在开始
The final race now starts
今天武状元之争
The candidates,
是由蒙古的博达尔多⋯
Po Ye Tat Tor from Mongolia
好⋯好
Bravo…
⋯对广东的苏察哈尔灿
And So Cha Ha Yee Chan from Canton
最后三分钟
Last call
苏察哈尔灿一赔十，博达尔多一赔一
So, one to ten Po, one to one
有没有搅错，赔率怎么差那么多？
Are you kidding, how can the betting rates differ so much?
一个是一赔十，一个是一赔一
One to ten for Chan? Kidding?
对苏灿那么没信心！
Why don't you have faith in Chan?
没办法，苏灿在举重项目弃权
That is, Chan defaulted in weight lifting
你看，博达尔多
Look, Po entered the final race
全部是满分进级，怎么比呢？
with full marks, it differs
现在是考状元，又不是当苦力
It's an examination of the Scholar of Martial Arts, not king of coolie
举重了得又有何用！
It's meaningless to be the champion of weight lifting
话不是这样说　　甚么？
- You shouldn't put it that way    - What?
这位同僚有见识
He is smart
我钻研了这场比赛很久
I've studied this race for a long time
也觉得个赔率有点古怪
I feel strange about the rate too
这个博达尔多外型俊朗，浑身有力
Po is smart and strong
但是未出赛行圈颈部就已经有白汗
But see the sweat of his neck
我猜可能是虚火
I think it's because he is getting tired
是吗？
Really?
但是这个苏察哈尔灿
But this So
怎样？怎样？
What do you think?
虽然沿途低著头
He has been disappointing the audience
但是能进入决赛是很困难的
But he has worked very hard
甚么？
What?
是洋文！即是有斗心
He tried very hard
所以我准备全押
So I want to bet on him
是吗？那你打算押多少？
How much do you want to bet?
八十万两！
800,000 taels
八十万两那么少？买够二百万两嘛
Why not 2 million taels?
怎么？为甚么你突然间看好他
What? Why are you so optimistic about Chan?
我看你分析得那么清楚
You have good analysis
给你说说
I feel Chan
我都觉得苏灿像赢定的
will be the champion
过来过来
Come on
我第二次全押
I want to bet more on him
是吗？
Really?
二百万两
2 million taels!
豪气！豪气
How generous!
为甚么你不下注？
Why don't you bet?
我下注干甚么？他是我的儿子
Why should I bet? He is my son
糟了！我少分析了这个
Shit, I miss one thing out of my calculation
少分析了甚么？
What?
血统
The blood
主考到
Here comes the Examiner
不是老郑主考吗？
What? Isn't Cheng the examiner?
请坐
Please take a seat
僧格林参？
Seng-ko-lin-ch'in?!
有甚么问题？
What's the problem?
他是博达尔多的叔叔
He is the uncle of Po
开始
Let's start
Start!
靶都射穿了！至少都多加两分
They should add 2 more marks for that powerful shoot
照道理是！照道理是
I do think so
苏灿靶上没有箭！博达尔多胜
So's arrow isn't on the target, Po won this section
有没有搅错！你老祖！要把戏？
Kidding? Damn you! They are cheating
考生上马！准备下一回合
The candidates please get on the horses
赵先生
Mr Chiu
你拿著这套袖箭！必要时有用
Take these with you, maybe you will find them useful
第二回合开始
Here comes the 2nd round
兵器都动了手脚？
They tricked again
太黑暗了！退票不赌行不行？
It's corrupt! May I give up the betting?
追回一局了
Chan won this race
你的票撕了没有
Did you tear the ticket?
没有
Not yet
有没有搅错？
Are you kidding?
还不认输？再来
Once again?!
重新开始，让你一手一脚
OK, let's start from the very beginning, I'll fight with a single hand and leg
免你说我欺负你
I won't take your advantage
你用这肮脏的手段来取得胜利？
How can you use such a dirty stance?
小子你睡醒了吗
Have you woken?
好棒呀！赢了
Bravo! He won
喝茶！喝茶
Have some tea
祝你好运
All the best!
这当然要用臀啦！还有别处可用吗？
What did you say?
是洋文
It's English
洋文
例上没有说明不准用暗器
There is no regulation stating that a weapon is not allowed
你先掉下来，这个回合判博达尔多胜
You fell down first, Po is the winner again
你个短命的老郑，竟敢骗我
Damn you Cheng! You betrayed me!
以后不要给我看见你
I will beat you to death
见一次打一次
if I see you again
不用了！你以后都不会见到他
Forget it, you won't see him anymore
为甚么？
Why?
我现在就去劈他
I am now going to kill him!
我那里有二百万输？
I don't have 2 million to lose!
只是说说而已
Just kidding
卑鄙无耻
You shameless
博达尔多三局两胜，是今科武状元
Po is the Scholar of Martial Arts
明明是我赢！我抗议
I did win! Objection
甚么事？
What are you doing?
镖有毒
The dart is poisoned
报应来了！死得好
He deserves it!
这枝有毒的镖是他自己的
He was poisoned by his own dart
他死了，我儿子就当状元？
Well, my son will be the Scholar then
那我现在不是发财了吗？
I am going to be rich!
对⋯
Yes!
你⋯你⋯
You… You…
光宗耀祖了⋯
Thank you, my ancestors!
有眼光
You have good judgement
大人，皇上说要亲自钦点
Sir, His Majesty wants to appoint the title himself
好
OK
武状元，我想问你几句作为朝廷纪录
I want to take a statement from you as record
你这次成功！会先感谢谁？
You won this time, who are you going to thank?
如霜姑娘
Miss Yushang!
如霜姑娘！会不会是他的娘？
Is Miss Yushang his mom?
万岁！万岁！万万岁
Long life to you!
平身
Please get up
谢皇上
Thank you
僧格林参，今科武状元是谁？
Who is the new Scholar of Martial Arts?
禀告皇上，是广东的苏察哈尔灿
Your Majesty, So Chan from Canton is the Scholar this year
苏察哈尔灿！参见皇上
Your Majesty, I am So Cha Ha Yee Chan
皇上，微臣有事启奏
Your Majesty, I want to report something
准奏
Go ahead
微臣查出苏察哈尔灿目不识丁
I have found that So is illiterate
怎可以答到考战略的题目呢？
So how could he answer the question paper of strategy?
分明有诈
That should be a trick
给朕拿文房四宝来
Take the stationery out!
是
Yes
苏察哈尔灿，马上写出你的名字来
So Cha Ha Yee Chan, write your name now
走运了！他懂得写名字
Thank God, he knows how to write his name!
懂写名字！懂写名字
He can write his name!
我不会写
I don't know how to write
你分明作弊
That's shit!
拉他出去斩
Kill him now
不要！不要
No! No!
皇上，作弊的是奴才
Your Majesty, I am the one who cheated
不关我儿子的事
It's none of his business
要斩就斩我吧
Just chop me to death
不对！应该斩我
No, you should kill me
对不起，阿爹
Sorry dad
其实我连自己名字都不会写
I don't know how to write my name
不用说！刚刚知道了
Stop, I have known it already
皇上！要斩就斩我吧
Your Majesty, I should be killed
斩我吧　　斩我吧
- Kill me    - No, kill me
斩我吧　　皇上！你还是斩我吧
- Kill me.    - Your Majesty, you'd better kill me
混帐！你们说要斩谁就斩谁吗
Shit, are you giving order?
你两父子同谋
You two cooperated to cheat me
吏部尚书按例判刑
The Secretary for Justice, announce the penalty for them
吏部尚书，快点出来！出来
Come out! Hurry up
我在这里！在这里
I am here!
他是吏部尚书？
He is the Secretary for Justice
苏察哈尔灿两父子罪犯欺君理应问斩
So's family should be sentenced to death
念在你是功臣之后！可免一死
But their ancestors achieved a lot for Ching, they can be exempted
但贪赃依例充公，枉法吗⋯
But, their fortune should be forfeited
你有没有执过法？
Have you carried out any military duty?
没有！我七年都没有到过军营
I haven't gone back to my camp for 7 years, I haven't done anything
没有执法即是没有枉法
So, he didn't miscarry out any duty
是这样的
So, the maximum penalty
皇上，依例最多判抄家的罪
is forfeiture of property only
这么轻？你有没有记错？
What? Are you sure?
奴才很公正的
I am fair
全都是依足基本法例办事
I judge it from the Law Book
那朕现在多加刑罚行不行？
Can I add something?
皇上说要加，当然没问题
Sure, since you are the Emperor
好！那朕就判你们两父子一辈子讨饭
I want them to be beggars for the rest of their lives
僧格林参
Why couldn't you find out
为甚么他作弊你没有查出来
they cheated during the examination?
这一次幸好有赵无极
Luckily Chiu reported it to me on time
赵无极，你揭发有功！朕会好好赏你
Chiu, you would be rewarded
身如柳絮⋯
I am wandering…
这是我爹的神主牌位，你也要没收
That's the spirit tablet of my dad, do you want to take it too?
这个香炉锅，你拿了也没用
It's useless for you
⋯历劫沧桑⋯鸳鸯扣
How poor are we…
宜结不宜解，苦相思⋯
I am thinking of my better half…
少爷
Young master,
从今天开始
from now on,
我想你要认真的学写字了
you'd be hardworking to learn how to write
苦相思，能买不能卖⋯
But I can't sell the affection…
师爷
Professor
我会学的
I will learn it
悔不该，惹下⋯
I regret that…
老爷，我会好好把小乌龟养大
Master, I will take good care of the little turtle
对不起，老爷
I am sorry
我们跟你一起这么久，蛋都没有生过
We haven't given birth to any baby of yours
不相干，不相干
It doesn't matter
是老爷办事不力
It's all my fault
若然老爷要的话，孩子多的是了
If I did better, you could have many babies
不过老爷有阿灿一个就够了
But I think Chan is enough for me
还在这干吗？快走
Why are you standing here? Go now
老爷，我们走了
Master, we are leaving
我们走了，老爷
We are leaving, master
走吧，走吧
Go, go now
安乐了
We are free
真开心
I feel so happy
太开心了
How happy are we!
进去，进去
Go in…
快点⋯
Hurry up…
为甚么他们给人家抄家还这样开心？
Why are they so happy?
笑死人了⋯
I am very happy
请进，请进⋯
Please go in…
欢迎⋯欢迎
Welcome…
孩儿，我们被抄家，我很想哭
Damn sequestration, I wanna cry, my son
不要！千万别丢脸
Hold it, don't lose our face
继续笑
Keep on laughing
孩儿，你刚才有没有留点银票傍身
Son. Have you kept any money?
没有！你呢？
No, how about you?
我忘记了
I forgot that
完蛋了！我俩真是完蛋了
Shit, damn sequestration!
善有善报，可怜我这个小乞丐⋯
Be merciful, please give money to us
孩儿！你看这个像不像阿爹？
Son, that guy is like dad
你指唱歌那个？
You mean the one who sings?
不是，是给钱的那个
No, the one who pays
他比唱歌那个更没良心
He is more disgusting than the one who sings
不是吧！多潇洒，各人眼光不同吧
Not exactly, he is smart
都怪老爹不好
Dad should be blamed
以前老叫你小乞丐！小乞丐
I always called you beggar
现在就真的要做了
Now, it becomes true
我并不相信这命运
What's wrong with you?
皇帝要我们做乞丐
The emperor wants us to be beggars
我们就乖乖当乞丐吗？
Do you think we'd be beggars?
以我这种人才和武艺
I am smart, I am keen in kung-fu fighting
天也不准我去当乞丐
Even the Gods won't let me be a beggar
这就是嘛
That's true
我那里像乞丐？
Am I like a beggar?
不像
No
小乞丐老乞丐，拿去买东西吧
Buy something to eat, you beggars
你真的当我们是乞丐？
You treat us as beggars?
混你的帐！你⋯
Damn you!
太过分了！吃饭吃饭
It's weird! Let's eat
阿灿，反正吃饱没事干
Chan, since we have nothing to do
让我在那边坐一会，说不定有晚饭吃
Let me take a seat, maybe we can have something to eat tonight
那你真的当自己是乞丐吗
You are treating yourself a beggar?
阿爹！不用担心
Dad, don't worry
想要钱都不需要去讨
I need no begging for money
不需要讨那里有钱呢？
How can you get money if you don't beg?
问人家借就行了
Just ask someone to give us money
兄弟，贵姓大名？
Pal, may I know your name?
牛大春
Nau Tai Chung
你身上有没有银两？
Do you have money?
有　　借来用用
- Yes    - Just give it to me
好的
OK
多谢
Thank you
我为甚么要给你钱？
Why should I give you money?
你问这么多干甚么！
Why do you ask so many questions?
那总该知道吧
But I should know the reason
知道要给，不知道也要给
Anyway, you should pay it
不行不行，还是弄清楚比较好
No, let's fix it up first
你拿来吧！问这么多干吗
Just give it to us, why are you asking so much?
放手
Hands off
你这样即是抢
You mean robbing?
强盗⋯
Robbery…
不是抢！我们是讨饭
I am not robbing, I am begging
原来你这两个臭东西的想骗我
Begging? How dare you, you beggar, you are cheating me!
别当我呆子！我很聪明的！
Don't you think I am stupid? I am smart, you know?
已两天了
Hey, two days passed,
天气越来越冷！肚子越来越饿
It's cold and I am hungry now
你想到没有？
Have you had any idea?
有办法，我有个朋友的阿姨的妹妹
I have a friend's girlfriend
正好住在京城
who is living in Peking
他早就向我透露很欣赏你
She always admires you
会有这回事？
Really?
是！如果你肯跟他交际一下
Yes, if you are willing to date her
我想他会帮我们忙先回广州
I think she will help us to go back to Canton
但是就要你老人家牺牲一下
But, you have to sacrifice
不知道你老人家意思⋯
Do you mean…
为了这个家，我甚么都可以做
For our family, just as you said
我知道太为难你了
I know it's very hard for you
别再说了！我们去见他
Cut the crap, let's go and find her
我早就跟你安排好了
I have arranged it
就在对面灯笼下穿红衣服的那个
The one wearing red dress who stands under the lantern, that's her
鬼
Ghost!
没问题吗
It's a benefit for you!
没问题！不过你先来，我跟在后面
Why don't you go yourself?
阿灿，胸口碎大石我还没玩过
Chan, I haven't tried this before
小心点
Be careful!
不用怕，我会很小心
Don't worry
确保你没有事
I'll take care of you
你也想赚点钱吃碗鱼翅吧？
You want to earn money for shark-fins, right?
对⋯
Right…
走开⋯走开
Get lost…
不许在这儿卖艺
No show here
大人，我们只想赚点钱
We just want to earn some money
回广州去
to go back to Canton
给我们一条生路，不要赶尽杀绝
Don't be that mean to us
皇上御旨
It's the Royal instruction that
苏察哈尔灿两父子终身行乞
the So's family'd be beggars for life
你们只可以当乞丐
You two can only be beggars
我是奉本子办事！人来
I am carrying out my duty only, men!
有　　将所有东西搬走
- Yes!    - Remove all the things
是
Yes
救命
Help!
赵大人！一个人搬不动
Master Chiu, it's hard for one to carry it
一个搬不动多上几个人
Ask more men to remove it
是
Yes
你们想怎么样？
What do you want?
不行，都搬不动　　让我来吧
- No, we can't move it    - Let me do it
那你是想打架吧？
You want a fight, don't you?
上次你在怡红院逃过一次
Last time you escaped from Yee Hung Hostel
这次你没有这胜券
But you won't be that lucky this time
这个人非同小可
He is powerful!
我一定要在第一招出尽力打败他
I've got to defeat him by one powerful strike
不然他就会有还击的机会
I can't give him another chance to counterattack
阿灿⋯
Chan…
阿灿
你的手脚跟全身经脉都给我打断
Your legs and hands are all broken by me
你一辈子都像废人一样！
You will be a cripple for the rest of your life
想用武功？没你份儿！
You want to fight? Not now!
不过，伸手讨几个钱还可以
But, you can beg for money
乖乖当乞丐吧
Be a good beggar
走⋯没事⋯走开
Go, go away…
不用怕阿灿，没事的，没事的⋯
Don't panic, Chan, it's OK
不用怕，没事的⋯
Don't panic, you'll be alright… Chan!
不用怕
Don't panic
那天我跟我儿子踏入试场
I went to the examination hall
再抬头一看那个试官
with my son,
你们猜他是谁？
don't you know who was the examiner?
就是僧格林参这个龟儿子
He is Seng-ko-lin-ch'in, that bastard
这个龟儿子跟我们父子俩有过节吗
He was the enemy of us!
一说到他我就气死了⋯
About our story…
不要说了，先吸口烟
Let me stop here first, I want a smoke
吸口烟提提神
It's better to smoke now
是的，好多了
Yes, it's better
这个王八蛋当日在怡红院
We let him go in
我们父子俩放他一马
the Yee Hung Brothel
想不到他恩将仇报
But he framed us in return
陷害我的儿子
He tricked my son
在兵器上全都动了手脚
during the examination
还好我儿子有真材实料⋯
But, my son was really smart and great
我要他武功盖世，状元之才
To be the greatest Kung-fu fighter, invincible
一人之下，万人之上
Be the top
那你做不做得到呢？
Can you do that?
做得到
Sure!
好
Well
待你做得到的时候就回来找我
Come back to me if you can do that
既然如此，我想我们要先定婚期
I think we should fix our wedding date first
因为做状元对我来说易如反掌
Because being the scholar is too simple for me
马上写出你的名字来
Write your name at once
我不会写
I don't know how to write
灿！怎么？
Chan, what's wrong with you?
又作恶梦？
Nightmare again?
别想这么多
Don't think so much!
虽然休息了两个月，手脚可以动了
Although you have taken 2 months' rest,
但是还没有完全好了
your legs and hands have not been totally recovered
哈尔叔　　来⋯
- Mr. Ha Yee    - Coming
阿爹出去找点食物回来
I am going to beg for food
然后煮最后一趟药给你喝
I will make the last herbal tea for you later
爹，又去讨饭
Dad, you go begging again?
讨饭当然要老夫出马
This job should be left to me
难道要你堂堂武状元⋯
You are the Scholar…
阿灿，原来当乞丐也不简单
Chan, to be a beggar,
有很多窍门
there are some lessons!
不是伸手出来就有钱的
You can't just show your hand and beg for money
至少要拿个砵子！这样才有身份
At least you should have a bowl, that represents your class
乞丐也论身份，真混帐
Is it ridiculous?
快点走
Hurry up
来了
I am coming
再不去就讨不到饭了
We can't beg for food if we are late!
是的⋯
Yes…
你以为自己是以前的大将军
You're not a master now.
给我点钱
Give me money please
没有没有，走吧
Go, go, I won't give you money
走，快走⋯别碍我做生意
Go, don't stop me from doing business
阿灿，阿爹出去了
Chan, dad is leaving
谢谢⋯
Thank you…
谢谢⋯谢谢
别那么吝啬吧，老兄？
Are you that mean?
你不会自己写？
Why don't you write it yourself?
我见你下班了，借你地方用一下吧
You are off duty, so I just want to lend it
你当我呆子吗？
Don't you think I am an idiot?
阿爹
Dad!
你甚么？
What are you doing?
好冷⋯阿灿！好冷⋯
I am cold… I am cold… Chan
好冷？糟糕了！你身体好熨
No, your body is as hot as fire
你病了？
Are you sick?
没有⋯没有
I am not…
这么晚了
It's late
阿爹出去讨些东西给你吃
I have to search for food
你快躺下吧，今天让我去
Lie down, I will go this time
你去讨饭？
Are you going for begging?
没有问题，我会有办法
I have my own way to get food
你休息一下
Take a rest now
我找到钱就回来带你看大夫
I will take you to the doctor after getting some money
你这浑小子为何不吃
You bastard, why don't you eat?
你不吃又怎能像阿爹般强壮
You should eat more so as to be strong!
快点吃
Finish it
吃不下了，我饱了
No, I am full
饱⋯饱也要吃，快点吃
You should take all the food
不吃吗！不吃就回家
OK, just forget it, let's go home
吃！快点吃，吃
Come on, eat them all
小朋友
Little kid!
甚么？
What?
可不可以⋯　　不可以
- May I…    - No
好心吧！福心吧！
Be merciful!
可怜我这个⋯小乞丐
Be merciful to me, please
我爹快要冷死了
My dad is dying!
小乞丐，这里有点碎碳你要不要
Beggar, do you want the broken charcoal?
多谢
Thank you
可不可以再给我多一点零钱
Can you give me some coins?
是你
It's you!
不是我
No, you are mistaken
姐姐！是他
Sister, it's him
不是他！不是他
No, no
姐姐⋯姐姐！苏灿
Sister, he is So Chan
等一下
Wait!
小姐，你找谁呀？
Miss, who are you looking for?
对不起，我认错人！
I am sorry, I was mistaken
小翠，去拿几个馒头出来
Tracy, take some dumplings out
你认错人了！他不是苏灿
You are mistaken, he is not So Chan
你很像我一个朋友
You are like my friend
以后没东西吃，就到我家取馒头
Come to get some dumplings if you get nothing to eat
我家里人少，吃不完
We always have surplus
馒头来了
Dumplings
拿去
Take it
谢谢⋯
Thank you…
姐姐
Sister,
要不是为了你，他也不会变成这样
he wouldn't be that poor if it were not for you
阿爹！怎么呢
Dad, what are you doing?
阿灿！我刚刚饿坏了
I can't stand the hunger
看见小孩子吃馒头，我借来咬一口
So I bit the dumpling of the kid
我这里有馒头！还给他
I have a dumpling, take it back
这样也可以吗？
Could I pay you another head
我斩了你个头再还给你可不可以？
if I chopped yours
你是状元爷吗？
Are you the Scholar?
是不是？是不是你？
Yes, are you the Scholar?
差点儿是
I was nearly the Scholar
真的！真是状元爷
He is the Scholar!
一定给面子状元爷
We should give him face
多谢⋯多谢
Thank you
等一等！相请不如偶遇
Hold it
相请不如偶遇，是否想请我们喝酒呢
Are they going to treat me some food?
给狗吃的饭到
The dog's rice
状元爷，吃完这饭就放你的爹
Sir, I will let your dad go if you eat the dog's rice now
甚么？
What's the matter?
吃吧
Come on
阿灿！你不能吃
Chan, don't eat that
你吃了后怎样见人？
You can't face the others if you eat this
阿爹年纪大没甚么大不了
Let's forget about me
老兄，说到底我是广州将军
Sir, I was a general in Canton
想怎样呀？
So what?
不要打
Stop fighting
站好
Stand properly
状元爷吃狗的饭
The Scholar eats the dog's food
爹，味道不错
Dad. It's quite delicious
尝尝⋯尝尝，来⋯来
Try some. Come on
好吃，是吗？
It's delicious, isn't it?
阿爹，你看
Dad, look!
有些肉丝在里面
There is a slice of meat here
甚么肉丝？是肉排
It's pork chop!
你俩比狗还要饿！
They are as hungry as dogs!
注定这辈子都吃狗的饭
Enjoy the dog food!
吃吧！快点吧！
Hurry, finish it
这碗饭太好吃了
That's too delicious!
这一口我想留下来作夜宵
I want to save it for midnight snack
多亏你想像得到
It's very clever of you!
真是天生当乞丐的料子
You deserve to be beggars
状元爷都要吃狗的饭
The Scholar is eating dog food
来！我们去吃人的饭吧
Come on, let's go and eat the man's food
苏老伯
Uncle So!
你是⋯
You are…
丐帮帮主就是我爹
My dad was the Master of the Beggars' Association
不如你俩加入丐帮，好不好？
Why don't you join our Beggars' Association
莫大叔，好不好
Uncle Mok, isn't it a good idea?
好
Good
丐帮是不是讨饭帮？
Isn't it the association for beggars?
是
Yes!
正好⋯现在我们当乞丐
That's right, we are being beggars
加入你们丐帮有个照应也好
It's wise to join the Beggars' Association so as to be taken care of
阿灿⋯他去哪儿呢？
Chan… where is that fool going?
阿灿呢？在哪里？
Where is Chan?
好，我们两个报名，两个
OK, we will join you!
灿⋯灿
Chan… Chan…
如霜！恭喜发财
Yushang, good year!
莫大叔！恭喜发财
Uncle Mok, happy new year!
这礼物是给你的
This is for you
多谢！多谢
Thank you
这两件衣服，一件给你，一件给阿灿
One cloth is for you and the other is for Chan
先把东西放下，先把东西放下
Thank you. Put it down first
有没有零钱？
Do you have any coins?
有
Yes!
有就拿来！来⋯　　干甚么？
- Give them to me, come on    - What for?
干甚么？过新年当然要利利是是
It's new year, you should receive a red packet
来，祝你身体健康
Come on, happy new year
恭喜发财
Good year!
你就青春美丽　　谢谢
- Wish you ever beauty    - Thank you
莫大叔，我们二老就两免了
Uncle Mok, we needn't give red packets to each other
阿灿呢？
How about Chan
阿灿？他由年三十睡到大年初一
Chan?
还没睡醒
He is still sleeping
他刚刚才睡！别把他吵醒
Don't wake him up
我做年糕给大家吃吧
I will cook you some new year cake
好！我帮你
Let me help you
新年还在睡觉
How can he sleep on the 1st day of this year?
真是没用的家伙！
He is useless
大家到齐了没？
Are you all here?
对付赵无极一定要团结丐帮
To fight against Chiu, we need a union of the Beggar's Association
我们要选出新帮主来主持大局
So we must choose a new master to be in charge of the association
如霜⋯如霜
Yushang…
对付三位长老的莲花落阵
To defeat the Lotus position of the three seniors
全靠你了
You should try your best
莫大叔！莲花落阵你也没把握
Uncle, I don't have faith to defeat them
以我现在打狗棒法的功力
Judging from my kung-fu now,
怎么可能打败三位长老当上帮主呢？
how can I defeat them and become the new master?
这颗大还丹，你吃了之后会功力大增
Take this Taiwan pill, after this, your power will be improved
不行！这颗大还丹是给你治内伤用的
No, this is the only medicine to cure your inner injury
我怎么能吃呢？
How can I take this?
不用担心不用担心
Don't worry,
想找人比武可以找我儿子
you can ask my son to fight for you
我儿子怎么说也是一个武状元
He was a scholar of Martial Arts
现在⋯
before…
⋯不！曾经
Before…
你看他懒洋洋的
Look at him, he is so lazy,
只会睡觉，怎能打架呢？
he knows sleeping only
连当乞丐的资格都没有
He is not even qualified to be a beggar!
你别那么坦白行不行？
Don't be that frank, can you?
你别那么大声好不好？
Don't shout that loudly, OK?
阿灿，不管人家现在怎么看不起你
Chan, no matter how they despise you,
老爹对你很有信心
I have faith in you
虽然现在你没有武功
Although you lost your power
但是以你的底子
With your background,
只要你肯出一点点力
only if you try hard,
必定会有一番作为
you can achieve something
我现在已经没有力，也不想再用力
But I am now powerless, I don't want to fight again
怎么会没有力呢？
You have power!
快打我一拳
Come on, beat me
这一拳蛮有力吗
See, that was powerful
所以我说，做人⋯
Well, being a people…
算了！不要再浪费时间
Forget it, don't waste time
还是让我多睡一会儿吧
Why don't you let me sleep?
你怎么把门锁上？
Why did you lock the door?
你慢慢睡吧
Enjoy sleeping
孩儿，我费尽心思才弄出这么大阵容
Son, I tried very hard to get this for you
你要多用点心把打狗棒法练好才行
Try hard to practise, be good
你爬得那么高干甚么？
Why do you go up?
就算你要我练打狗棒法
Even you want me to practise Kung-fu,
你总该留个棒子给我吧
you should give me a waddy first
抱歉抱歉！你接好了
I am sorry, catch it
天将降大任于斯人也
Before being appointed an important task,
必先劳其筋骨，饿其体肤，苦其心智
God will give you severe training for soul and flesh.
苦海无涯？你写的？
Did you write it?
写得这么丑，把它擦掉也对
It's ugly, it's right to wipe it away
乞丐？
Hey, beggar?
是
Yes
我也是
Me too
恭喜你
Congratulations
有没有东西吃？　　没有
- Is there anything to eat?    - No
正好我有
Luckily, I have
这造型不去讨饭博人家同情，真可惜
See your look, it's a waste for you not to beg
这与你无关！
None of your damn business
你当乞丐也这么懒
You are too lazy to be a beggar!
同行都瞧不起你了
Your fellows despise you
我以前到那里都被人家看重
I was always respected by others
还不是落得这个下场
But now, I am despised
我正好刚刚相反
Dislike from you,
我一辈子没被人瞧得起过
no one respected me before
听我说，先别走，听我说
Listen to me. Don't go!
记得有一次，在广东
I remembered once in Canton
请我吃饭喝酒嫖妓过夜
A fool paid my living, including hooking
这样的人也有
What a weird man
帅哥，我记得你
Kid, I remembered you
臭小子，我也记得你
Me too
废话少说
Hey, hurry up
还我钱让我顶一下
Repay my money, I am in urgent need
如果我有钱
If I had money,
我也不用在这儿挨馒头
I wouldn't be a beggar!
不过你不用怕，你有恩于我
But, don't worry, you were my benefactor,
我会报答你的
I will repay you one day
多谢，心领
Thank you very much
给你钱也没有用
But, you can't buy back what you lost
也买不回你失去的东西
even if you have money again
我失去了甚么？
What did I lose?
尊严，自信
Pride and faith
还有你心爱的女人
And your woman too
你究竟是何人？
Who are you?
好说，在下洪日新，外号老鬼新
I am Hung Yat-sun, nicknamed Old Bag Sun
乞丐中辈份最高，字号最老
I am the most senior one among the beggars
做乞丐有甚么不好？
It's good to be a beggar
想走就走，想睡就睡
You can do everything you want
你也可以一样吗
You can do the same
你说，你想要甚么？我成全你
Tell me, what do you want? I will make your wish come true
我想重新做人
I want to be human again
怎么你觉得你不像人吗？
Don't you think you are not human-like?
一直都不算是
Not at all
所以你才会弄成这样，年青人
So you have to be a beggar now
非常好，非常好
Very good! Very good!
实不相瞒，我看阁下从头到脚趾头
But I won't cheat you, from your head to toes
没有一个地方不露乞丐形格
Every part of you is beggar-like
又如何？
So what?
即是说阁下注定讨饭讨一辈子
That means, you will be a beggar for your life
还是不跟你说，我想睡一会儿
I don't want to talk to you, I want to sleep first
先别走！行行出状元
Don't go, you can achieve in your profession
如果我没看错
From my judgement,
你会是乞丐中的霸主
you will be the king of beggars
乞丐中的霸主？那是甚么？
King of beggars, what does that mean?
还是乞丐
That is beggar
我不管你是甚么人，我不想再跟你说
I won't care who you are, I just want to stop the conversation
请你让开，不要碍著我睡觉
Please step aside, don't stop me from sleeping
你找死吧？
Damn you!
不是⋯你说要睡觉
No… I just want to sleep
我只想跟你一块儿
with you
神经病
Idiot!
年青人，我们梦中相见
Kid, see you in the dream
佛前金座，罗汉归位
Before the Buddha, the Disciples return to your position
降龙，伏虎
To suppress the dragon and tiger
苏灿，你享尽人间富贵
So Chan, you enjoyed the prosperity of the world
亦尝尽人间苦楚
And you tasted the bitter fruit of the world too
如今大彻大悟
Now you regret it
我就以洪七公第七代传人的身份
On behalf of Master Hung
封你为睡梦罗汉
I appoint you to be the “Sleeping Disciple”
醉回梦生法，传授你睡梦罗汉拳
Now, I will teach you the “Sleeping Disciple's Fist”!
希望你好好利用，接招
Hope you can make good use of it. Come on
前辈⋯
Senior…
苦尽甘来？
The bitter past
万岁！万岁！万万岁
Long life to you…
白羊降世，天理循环
Here comes the White Goat
真空家乡，无生老母，赐我神通
My mother, give me power
超渡众生
To save the people!
皇帝明天会到成都狩猎
Tomorrow the Emperor will go hunting
我会用献上美女的理由接近他
I will send him a pretty girl, so as to get close to him
宛玲，你明天可能要牺牲一下色相
Yuen Ling, you should seduce him tomorrow
是
Yes
只要明天杀了皇帝
If we can kill the Emperor,
天下就尽在我手
I can take over his reign
荣华富贵绝对少不了你们
I will give you a share of wealth!
万岁！万岁！万万岁
Long life to you
长老
Senior!
回去再说
Let's go back now
长老
Senior!
我们走
Let's go!
长老
Senior!
我们追　　不用追了！
- Let's chase them    - Stop!
皇上快要出发
The Emperor is setting off soon
你杀了我的女人⋯
You killed a woman…
⋯我要把你献给皇上
You should replace her as a gift to the Emperor!
怎么？没有人敢上来当帮主
No one dares come up to fight for the leadership?
叫莫老三把打狗棒交出来
Ask Mok to give us the “Dog Hitting Waddy”!
莫大叔跟你姐姐到底到哪处？
Where have they been?
我怎么知道
I don't know,
刚才我听见莫大叔跟姐姐说了几句话
I saw them chat,
就出去了
then they went away
难道他俩有暧昧关系？
Is there any affair between them?
现在开始选帮主
Now, we are going to choose the new leader
莫大叔⋯
Uncle Mok…
真的被你嚇我一跳
I am scared,
还以为你不会来了
I think you won't come back
没事吗？　　姐姐呢？
- How is it?    - Where is sister?
你姐姐给赵无极抓了
Your sister is caught by Chiu
我们要找人上去选帮主
We'd better find someone to compete for the leadership
到底派谁上去呢？
Who should go?
让我去
I'll do it
莫大叔
Uncle Mok
不如让我试试
Why don't you let me try?
阿灿
Chan,
你不是九代弟子，快下来
you are not qualified, come down
既然你挑不出好的，我可以教育你！
Since you don't have a good candidate, I'll give you some advantage
阿灿，你不要以为好玩
Chan, it's not a game
你会没命的！快下来
You will be killed, come down
没相干，我的命早就当没了
It doesn't matter, I have forgotten my life already
废话！丢他
Bullshit, throw him to death
既然如此，我就成全你
Well, I will make your wish come true
他在干吗？
What is he doing?
睡觉？
Sleeping
这一招难道就是⋯
Isn't this stance…
新师叔的睡梦罗汉拳？
Uncle Sun's “Sleeping Disciple's Fists”?
布阵
Set the position!
天亮了没有
Is it dawn?
各位不好意思
I am sorry!
我赢了
I won
你打赢我们有甚么用？
What is the use for defeating us?
你又不会打狗棒法
You don't know how to use the “Dog Hitting Waddy”.
你不配当帮主
You are not qualified to be the leader of us
打狗棒！是吗
“Dog Hitting Waddy”?
棒棒都打狗
It's for hitting dogs
谁说我不会打狗棒法？
I do know how to use this waddy!
不像打狗棒法
But it's different from the standard stances!
也蛮厉害！
It's quite powerful!
他打断了打狗棒
He broke the waddy!
他打断我们镇帮之宝！我们杀了他
He broke the treasure of our Association, let's kill him!
洪七公在此谁敢放肆
I am Master Hung, who dares go against me?
我当年定下帮规
I set the rules of the association
任何弟子破了莲花落阵
Any student who defeated the Lotus Position
都有资格当帮主
could be the leader
你们是不是全忘掉了？
Have you all forgotten?
丐帮之所以成为天下第一大帮
We becomes the biggest association
全因为团结两个字
because of being united
我洪某当年留下打狗棒
I left you the “Dog Hitting Waddy”,
目的只是留给大家作为留念
is just for memory
棒的本身并不代表甚么
The waddy is meaningless
但是你这些蠢蛋居然当宝
But you fools take this as treasure
还为了争夺它弄到丐帮四分五裂
And fight among yourselves for this damn waddy!
五年没有帮主在位！你们惭不惭愧？
In these five years, you have had no leader, don't you feel shy?
苏灿现在把棒打断了
So Chan broke the waddy,
以后大家没得争
so you won't fight for this anymore
绝对是有功没有过
He is correct to do so
这个年青人！虽然资历低
This youngster is so junior,
但是天才横溢！聪明绝顶
but he is a genius, a smart ass
还是我洪某的传人洪日新亲手提携
He is being taught by my disciple Hung Yat Sun
谁要对付他就是对付我
Who doesn't respect him is going against me too
你们不只要选他当帮主
You should respect him,
还要交出你们的爱心
your new leader, and you'd love him,
来爱护他！关怀他！常常请他喝茶
whole-heartedly, to care much for him, maybe, treat him dinner
那我洪某在天之灵
Then, although I am in heaven,
定会保佑丐帮生意兴隆！千秋万世
I will bless all of you, all the best
是真的还是假的？
Isn't it true?
宁可信其有不可信其无
You'd better trust it
洪七公显灵
Master Hung's soul talked to us,
天有眼，我们有福
we are blessed
就这样瞒天过海，我果真是天才！
They are easily to be cheated, I am really a genius!
大家有饭吃了
We'll have better living
发生甚么事？
What happened?
参见帮主
Let's greet the new Master
很棒
Bravo…
莫大叔！我儿子有一套吗
Uncle Mok, my son is really great!
想不到你学会睡梦罗汉拳
I can't guess you have learnt the “Sleeping Disciple's Fists”?!
由现在开始，你就是丐帮帮主
From now on, you are the new leader of us
这一本是降龙十八掌
This is the book of “Dragon Suppressing Stances”
还有大还丹都交给你
And, I will give you the Taiwan Pill
希望你好好领导丐帮
Hope you will be a good leader
我只想尽快救回如霜
I just want to save Yushang as soon as possible
如霜总算没看错你
Yushang didn't make a wrong choice
好棒！帮主好棒！
Bravo! Bravo!
莫大叔⋯莫大叔！你怎么呢？
Uncle Mok, how are you?
莫大叔，莫大叔
Uncle Mok!
莫大叔⋯莫大叔
Uncle Mok…
长路漫漫伴你闯
带一身胆色与热肠
寻自我觅真情
停步处视作家乡
投入命运万劫火
那得失怎么去量
驰马荡江湖
灿哥
Chan,
降龙十八掌的心法你真的明白了？
do you understand everything written in this book?
你别当我是呆子？
Don't think that I am so foolish
我得到大还丹的帮助
After getting the help of Taiwan Pill
全身经脉已经回复正常，内力大增
My initial power is increased
降龙十八掌首十七掌我已经领会到
I can control the 17 stances
但是第十八式「杀龙有悔」
But the last stance,
又没有图又没有文字
there is no picture or description of it
我怎么看都不明白
I can't understand at all
最糟糕的是莫大叔已经不在，那怎办
But Uncle Mok is dead, what'll we do now?
没甚么法子了！
Just go ahead
无论如何我也先出发去救如霜
No matter how, I have to save Yushang first
迎入日月万里风
笑揖清风洗我狂
来日醉卧逍遥
宁愿锈蚀我缨枪
你们到大营去看那儿准备好没有？
Check whether the camp is ready or not?
是
Yes!
赵无极
Chiu,
你带这个女人来是甚么意思？
why do you bring this woman here?
我知道皇上喜欢美女
I know the Emperor loves pretty women
所以我献上一美女给他
So I want to send him this gift
我想见一见皇上
And I want to meet him too
皇上并没有诏见，你别惊动他
There is no order from the Emperor
人来，带这个女人入营
Men, come and take this woman to the camp
是
Yes
走吧
Go!
大人，好一阵子不见，气色不错
Sir, you look great!
你应该回到自己的岗位
I think you should go back
不要擅离职守
to your own position
是
Yes
启禀皇上
Your Majesty,
赵大人带了个女人来献给皇上
Officer Chiu brings this woman to you
女人？
Woman?
赵无极这个人
Chiu knows my hobby!
我先去沐浴更衣，稍后带他来见我
I want to take a bath first, bring her to me later
是
Yes
这个王八蛋又想见皇上
This bastard wants to see the Emperor,
再让你多见几次，不是连官都没得当
if I let him see His Majesty often, my post will be taken away
人来
Men
大人
Sir
看看发生甚么事　　是
- Check what has happened    - Yes
大人，树林里有一大队人马
Sir, there are many people coming from the forest
甚么人马？
Who are they?
不知道
I don't know!
放狼烟
Release the alarm smoke
戒备
Be alert
是
Yes
前面大营放狼烟，大家戒备
There is smoke ahead, let's get armed
是
Yes
臭乞丐？
Damn you beggars
苏察哈尔灿，你搅甚么鬼？
So Chan, what are you doing?
没有！只是想向你讨个钱
Nothing, I just want to beg for money
岂有此理！你是不是不想活？
Shit, do you want to be killed
不想活的是你
It's you who will be killed
赵无极阴谋造反
Chiu wants to raise a rebellion,
现在还带人杀皇帝去
he is going to assassinate the king
你还那么傻头傻脑！
You fat-headed
你以为你是谁
Who do you think you are?
胆大包天！竟敢诬告官员？
How dare you frame the courtier?
再行一步格杀勿论
I will kill you if you step forward
阿灿，对方这么多人马我们怎么打？
Chan, how can we fight with them?
长老　　在
- Senior    - Yes
其他人马呢？
Where are the rest of our men?
其他人马正在赶来
They are coming
没时间再等了
We have no time,
你们留下来接应其他兄弟
you stay here to wait for the others
我先上
I will go first
我稍后跟来
I will follow
真的才好
Be serious
帮主，你放心去吧
Master, don't worry
我现在死定了？放心去
Am I going to die?
说句吉利话行不行？
Say something lucky, OK?
行！恭祝你福寿与天齐
Sure! Happy birthday to you…
庆贺你生辰快乐
Happy birthday to you…
年年都有今日⋯
够了够了
That's enough
还没唱完
I haven't finished
等我走了你再才唱　　好的
- Go on after I've left    - Sure
前面放狼烟，一定有人打草惊蛇
There is smoke ahead, someone must have alarmed them.
准备麒麟烟　　是
- Get ready the Unicom Smoke.    - Yes.
攻入大营
Attack the main camp.
作反了！这些狗贼真的作反了
Rebel! Help!
太可恶
They should be killed
射不死你的那个人才是最可恶
The one who didn't kill you should be killed
糟糕！毒烟吹向皇上大营
Shit, the poisoned smoke
这次真的完了
is blowing to the Royal camp
不是！风向转了
No, the wind direction changed
对！等等我
Yes, wait for me
丐帮再不撤退，格杀勿论
If the beggars don't retreat now, we will kill with no mercy
你们看这边
Have a look
天理教的麒麟烟
The Unicom Smoke of the Tin Li Sect
大家镇定点！用尿可以解毒
Be calm, urine is the antidote to the poison
撒尿⋯撒尿⋯
Come and piss
那我该怎么办？
How about me?
不怕！我的尿多，分一点给你
Don't worry, I can give you some urine
来⋯拿著它
Come on, hold it
冲！
Rush in!
形势如何？
How is the situation?
託皇上鸿福，风向转变
Thanks for Your Majesty's luck, the wind direction changed
毒烟已吹不过来
The smoke is going in the other direction
四围营和左右护翼情况怎么样？
How about our armies?
都全军覆没，皇上
They are all dead
拿刀来
Bring me the sword
不要皇上，皇上⋯
Don't… don't!
不要阻我，走开
Get lost! Get lost!
皇上，很危险的！不要走
Your Majesty, it's dangerous, don't go!
不去！难道坐在这里等死吗？走开
Get lost, don't you want to wait for death? Get lost
我叫你们走开
You are ordered to get away
不要走
You can't go!
护驾
Protect me
阿灿？
Chan?
如霜
Yushang
你怎么来到这里的？
How did you get here?
怎么来？就说来话长
It's a long story
昨天晚上我未吃夜宵就临夜起程
We left our base last night
攀过金山岭
We reached the Great Wall
到今天早上已经身在万里长城
this morning
我们停了半个时辰吃早饭
We stayed one hour for lunch
我还小个便
I pissed once
是吗？　　是
- Really?    - Yes
我本来想找蕃薯吃
Then I want to eat a sweet potato
谁知道只是馒头
But only dumplings left
你知道的，馒头根本不合我胃口
You know, I don't like eating dumplings
微臣救驾来迟，望皇上恕罪
I am late to save you, please forgive me
保护皇上
To protect the Emperor
是
Yes
你这个叛贼
You betrayer!
捉住他
Catch him
皇上
Your Majesty
狗皇帝，把你的江山交给我
You bastard, give your kingdom to me
你说甚么？
What are you telling him?
是你？
It's you
是我！苏乞儿
Yes, I am Beggar So
苏乞儿？你不是在乞丐窝里睡觉吗
Why don't you sleep in your hut?
是！你说起都有点困
Well, I am a little bit sleepy
睡罗汉？
“Sleeping Disciple”?
失礼！你披头散发的样子都蛮像乞丐
Yes. Look at you, you are like beggar too
有没有兴趣加入我们丐帮？
Are you interested to join us?
想不到你这条臭死鱼都可以复活
I can't guess you could recover!
是！这都是拜你所赐
Yes, it's all because of you
你已出全力？我还没出力
Did you generate all your force? I didn't
蠢蛋！普天之下除了降龙十八掌
Fool, only the “Dragon Suppressing Stances” scare me
甚么武功我都不放在眼内
I won't give a damn to any other stances
降龙十八掌第七式
“Dragon Suppress Stances”
飞龙在天
“Dragon in the sky”
神龙摆尾
“Dragon swings its tail”
乌龙偷心
“Dragon steals the heart”
双龙出海，战龙在田
Dragon swims, dragon in the field,
龙飞凤舞，伏虎降龙⋯
dragon dances…
⋯缩龙成寸，龙蛇混杂
Dragon's descendant,
龙的传人龙凤呈祥⋯
dragon's wish…
⋯龙马精神，望夫成龙⋯
Dragon's spirit, dragon's couple
打完收工
Finished
怎么得十七掌？太可惜了
You can't finish the last stance,
如果你学会第十八掌
you can defeat me
就一定可以打赢我
after learning the 18th stance
不过你没有这个机会
But you have no chance
阿灿！
Chan!
我想到了，原来头十七掌融合一起
I've got it. Just mix the 17 stances,
就是第十八掌
it's the 18th stance then
我实在太聪明了
I am too smart!
第十八掌－杀龙有悔
The 18 stance, “It's a regret to kill the Dragon”!
阿灿，你没事吧？
Chan, are you alright?
你看我的姿势，说有事没有？
See, don't you think I am alright?
你的姿势是很帅
Your pose is really smart
可是你的样子很有问题
But your look is awful!
傻瓜！我没事
Idiot, I am fine
今天晚上洞房都没问题
I can marry tonight
这么厉害
You are great!
阿灿⋯你没事吧
Chan! Are you okay?
赵无极呢
Where is Chiu?
到处都是
He is around
到处都是？
Around?
他已经化为烟尘
He became ashes
化为烟尘咁沙尘？挑！
Damn it!
报告帮主
Master
赵无极的人马都给我们捉住
Chiu's fellows have all been caught by us
辛苦了各位兄弟
Thank you, buddies
如霜
Yushang
你记不记得我们之间还有一个协议
We have an agreement, do you remember?
记得！一人之下！万人之上
Yes, be the top of all
盖世武功！状元之才
Invincible
可惜我始终都当不成状元
But, I can't be the Scholar
是！不过我不喜欢状元
But I don't like Scholar at all
我喜欢乞丐嘛
I love beggars.
你先！我稍后跟上
You first, I will go after you
僧格林参，你竟不分青红皂白
Seng-ko-lin-ch'in, you are really a fool
你引狼入室
You bring a thief to harm me
朕现在贬你为小乞丐
Now, you are titled to be a beggar
你当乞丐很好，看你的样子很有天分
You have potential to be a beggar
明天到城隍庙报到
Report duty in the temple tomorrow
有事报我的名字就行
If there is anyone bullies you, just tell them my name
多谢帮主，多谢帮主关照
Thank you, thank you master
苏灿，你有甚么要求？
So Chan, what do you want as reward?
你真没话跟朕说？
Don't you have anything to tell me?
有甚么好说呢？走
Nothing special, let's go
抱我起来
Pick me up
苏英雄！苏英雄
Mister So!
放下来
Put me down
你别以为救过朕
Although you have saved me,
你对朕不敬，朕一样会杀了你
if you don't respect me, I will kill you
你要杀我就不会这样跟我说话
If so, you needn't squat to talk to me
不要动，否则还碍眼
Don't move, it'll attract their attention
其实我跟你没醪没轕
Actually we have no relation,
真没甚么好谈
we have nothing to chat about
你丐帮弟子几千万
You have billions of fellows.
你一天不解散，朕怎么安心？
Your force makes me worry
丐帮有多少弟子不是由我决定
The number of fellows doesn't depend on me,
而是由你决定
but you
我？
What?
如果你真的英明神武，令到国泰民安
If you are great, making the society peaceful and wealthy,
谁会愿意当乞丐？
no one wishes to be a beggar, right?
有道理，有道理　　好自为之吧
- It's reasonable    - Be smart
不过
But,
你总该给朕一点面子，让朕好下台
give me some face
好
Yes
皇上吉祥
Long life…
万岁万万岁　　平身
- … to Your Majesty    - Get up
兄弟！认得我吗？
Pal, do you know me?
化成灰也认得你！臭乞丐
Of course! You beggar
揹著女儿，博取同情？
You beg with your girl, you think I'll give you money out of mercy?
是！施舍点吧
Yes, please give me money
乞丐就是不给！快滚
No mercy, go away
不给不行
No, you should pay me
应份的！兄弟
It's a must, pal
奉旨乞食？有没有搅错？
A must? Kidding?
没有搅错！爽手点！
It's true, be quick
怕了你
It's bad luck to meet you
先别走
Stop
又怎么？
What?
还有一家大小的！给多点
See my family? Give more
添多少？
How much?
没有一千都给八百
Not less than a thousand, got me?
还不快谢谢人家？
Say thank you now
谢谢
Thank you, uncle
快点吃吧
Hurry up
跟住我⋯走吧⋯
Follow me… go…